The executioner in a killing cannot also be the judge and the jury.
When the police kill young black men within the community
and then they're told that they should trust the process of justice,
when the same process of justice has proven to be untrustworthy, unreliable and dishonest,
then you have to prepare for a second kind of response.
And over the years, we have constantly heard this narrative
about young men shooting at the police and missing,
the police shooting back and hitting,
and then they find no gun, no weapon, no evidence whatsoever
with multiple eyewitnesses that have seen that the police were lying.
From the Trumacet 5 who were murdered in a home,
including a 15-year-old and a 17-year-old,
to the Movar 3 of whom, again, they said were shooting at them,
and then video evidence showed that they were lying,
and to the evidence of chief forensic pathologist, Dr. Valerie Alexandrov,
who said the police are not telling the truth.
Men who were running away, shot in the back,
are referred to by the police as forwardly shooting at them.
To the young brother, Romney, of whom they said killed the police officer,
Jilt, found out that they were lying, they're lying all the time.
To Shaquille McCoy, Dylan Vandiski, Billy Tuse, and so many others.
So how could you tell the young people,
trust that process, trust that system,
when that system has proven to them that it is not on their side at all.
When the Honorable Minister Louis Farrakhan was in Trinidad in 1996,
and he spoke of the gene pair complex, he spoke about justice.
And he said the symbol for justice is the scale.
The scale represents balance, which means equality on both sides.
But if one side is deprived of balance, and the scale is tipped,
that imbalance in the scale of justice is translated into imbalance in the stability of the mind
on the victim of the injustice, who now reacts in an imbalanced way mentally,
and seeks to commit and perpetrate acts of terrorism, or anti-socialism,
or to be violent and enraged and insane.
And because there's no justice in the land,
you're seeing these kinds of reactions out on the street.
So we cannot expect the youth to have faith in the court system
when the court system simply exclusively favors some as opposed to others.
But my advice, though, would be to our people out on the streets in the communities
that, one, when we're rioting or protesting,
that we don't do damage to the same surroundings
that we would have to eventually go back and seek prosperity in
and make a living from, especially in including our natural environment.
Which leads me to point number two.
When it comes to getting back at the enemy,
and you want to hit the enemy where it hurts,
do so in the only field where he respects, which is economics.
So let's withhold our money, pool our resources,
support the businesses in our community,
and open entrepreneurship projects
where we can circulate economic strength within our community.
And then and only then will they respect us in the way that they should.
And point number three, let us not just mobilize, but let's organize.
There's a difference between mobilization and organization.
Mobilization is when there's a problem or an issue in the community,
we get together temporarily to react and respond to it.
So we mobilize and light a fire or block a road,
or we engage in some collective action.
But organization is when before something even happens negatively
within our community that we're already combined,
and we've already brought together our strengths
with one aim, goal, vision, destiny, direction, and purpose.
And we're able to initiate action instantly and immediately
to protect ourselves and get justice
instead of through anger and rage reacting on the spot.
So am I saying that when the people are out there
lighting the fires and the tires and enlarged numbers
and throwing stones at the police,
some are saying, yes, light more fires.
Others are saying, no, let's go back home.
What you need is a balance between the two.
Keep the passion, keep the energy, keep the strength.
You can even keep the rage.
But don't use it for destruction.
Use it for construction.
And let's pool our resources, come together.
Hit them with the economics.
Stop buying their products.
And then we will be able to strengthen ourselves
as a community should be strong.
Those are just my simple thoughts.